Adersh A

Adersh Bhavanam Karuvatta South P.O, 690517 Alappuzha, India

adershaniyan1998@gmail.com

Linkedin

8848998277

Profile

Data Engineer with morethan 3 years of experience in healthcare, worked in cloud data platforms, building and managing data lakes and data warehouses, optimizing ETL workflows, and analyzing transactions. Focused on delivering reliable and efficient data solutions.

Skills

AWS Cloud SQL Python PySpark Databricks Snowflake

Experience

2021/10 – present India

Cognizant Technology Solutions India Pvt. Ltd | Data Engineer

2021 - 2023

Projects:

Cerner to Genius platform(Databricks) data migration
 Client: Gainwell Technologies | 08/2024-Present

Technologies Used:

Cloud Platform: Databricks, AWS S3

Language: PySpark, Python

Responsibilities:

- Involved in developing data ingestion pipelines in Databricks to process data from AWS S3 across various layers using scheduled workflows.
- Analyzed and converted SQL queries from source database for target compatibility and implemented business logic transformations.
- Designed and built PySpark based unit testing frameworks for different layers to ensure data consistency and accuracy.
- NDW : National Datawarehouse Modernization Client: Blue Cross Blue Shield Association (BCBSA) | 2021 - 08/2024

Technologies Used:

AWS Services: DMS, Lambda, S3, Athena, Glue, SNS, Eventbridge, CloudWatch

Database: **IBM DB2**Language: **Python**

Responsibilities:

- Developed and performed SQL queries to analyze intial meatadata checks and RCA Validation using complex queries.
- Handled file formats such as CSV, JSON and Parquet as part of the migration and enhancement strategy.
- Actively involved in developing a key data pipeline to process over 100 TB of data from on-premise systems using multiple loading strategies using AWS DMS.
- Developed and automated AWS lambda functions to retrieve AWS DMS log details and automated data consolidation with AWS Cloudwatch, SNS and S3.
- Designed and developed a Data validation framework using Python, integrating AWS Glue, lambda, S3, and Athena to automate the testing process and reporting via AWS Eventbridge and SNS.

- Worked with AWS Glue job to leverage Apache Hudi data management framework to reconcile incremental data on top of S3 Datalake to provide data consistency and accuracy.
- Automated reconciliation data stats ingestion using AWS Glue Crawler, Data Catalog and S3, enabling real-time querying through AWS Athena.
- Designed and implemented automated email reporting using Amazon SES, integrating AWS Lambda and Eventbridge for trigger based execution and scheduled delivery with cron expressions.
- Collaborated with Devops, Architects and QA to deploy AWS resources using CloudFormation templates and conducted knowledge transfer sessions for downstream teams.
- Worked in an Agile environment using Jira for sprint planning, task tracking, and collaboration.

Education

2017/08 – 2021/07

Bachelor of Technology

College of Engineering Trivandrum

Completed Industrial Engineering with 7.55 cgpa

2015/06 – 2017/03

Higher Secondary

S.N.M HSS, Purakkad

Completed higher secondary education with 92%

Certificates

- AWS Certified Solutions Architect Associate 🛮
- AWS Certified Cloud Practitioner
- SnowPro Core Certification 🖸
- Microsoft Certified: Azure Fundamentals 🛮